Xiao Wuyi?
เซียวอู๋อี
Where did he hide the divorce papers?
เอาหนังสือหย่าไปซ่อนไว้ที่ไหนนะ
What were you and Mao doing just now?
เมื่อครู่ท่านกับอาเม่าไปไหนกันมา
Archery match.
ประลองธนูไง
Between you two?
พวกท่านสองคนหรือ
Why the archery match?
ประลองธนูอะไรกัน
So who emerged victorious?
แล้วสุดท้ายใครชนะ
What do you think?
เจ้าคิดว่าไงล่ะ
Well...
เจ้า
Who do you hope ended up winning?
เจ้าอยากให้ใครชนะล่ะ
As the Commander of the Beifu Army, you competed with Mao in archery.
ท่านเป็นถึงผู้นำทัพเป๋ยฝู่ มาประลองยิงธนูกับอาเม่า
You must've won unfairly.
ท่านก็ต้องชนะอย่างไม่สมเกียรติอยู่แล้ว
Where is my hairband?
ผ้าผูกผมของข้าล่ะ
W-What hairband?
ผ้า... ผ้าผูกผมอะไร
The hairband I gave you
ก็ผ้าผูกผมที่ข้าใช้ปิดตาให้ท่าน
for you to cover your eyes during the match!
ในสนามประลองเมื่อครู่ไง
I threw it away.
ทิ้งไปแล้ว
You threw it away? Who allowed you to do it?
ทิ้งไปแล้วหรือ ใครใช้ให้ท่านทิ้งมันไปเล่า
Didn't Xiao Wuyi say he had thrown it away?
เซียวอู๋อีบอกว่าเขาทิ้งไปแล้วมิใช่หรือ
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[ชะตารักกระดูกปักษา]
[Episode 14]
[ตอนที่ 14]
Xiao Wuyi has gotten you the travel permit.
เซียวอู๋อีเอาหนังสือผ่านด่านมาให้เจ้าแล้ว
You only need to sign it.
แค่ลงนามบนนี้ก็ได้แล้ว
I wonder when I will be able to come back here again.
ไม่รู้ว่าเมื่อไหร่จะได้กลับมาอีก
Actually, I quite like this place.
ที่จริงข้าค่อนข้างชอบที่นี่นะ
[Palace of Eternal Peace]
[ตำหนักหย่งอัน]
Brother, why do you want to keep them?
เหตุใดท่านพี่จึงให้พวกนางอยู่ต่อ
Is it for
ใช่เพราะนางรำ
that dancer named Chan?
ที่ชื่ออาฉานคนนั้นไหม
She does
หน้าตาของนาง
look somewhat
มีส่วนคล้าย
like Jiayu.
เจียอวี๋อยู่จริง ๆ
Take them to the Directorate of Attendants.
ส่งพวกนางไปยังกรมฝ่ายในเถอะ
Understood.
ขอรับ
Brother,
ท่านพี่
are you really willing
ท่านทำใจที่จะปล่อยให้
to let Jiayu leave?
เจียอวี๋จากไปจริง ๆ หรือ
Yaoyao loves freedom.
เยาเยาชอบอิสระ
Right now, I
ข้าในตอนนี้
can't keep her.
รั้งนางไว้ไม่ได้
Wuyi also said that
แม้แต่อู๋อีก็บอกว่า
if I can bring peace and prosperity
หากข้าปกครองต้าเย่ให้สงบสุข
to Ye
บ้านเมืองผาสุก
and turn the places Yaoyao loves
เปลี่ยนดินแดนที่เยาเยาใฝ่ฝัน
into a paradise,
ให้กลายเป็นแดนสุขาวดีได้หมดละก็
that would also be a way of loving her.
ก็เป็นการรักนางอีกวิธีหนึ่ง
As long as I can seize the supreme power
ขอเพียงข้ากุมอำนาจที่สูงสุด
in this Jiankang Palace...
ในตำหนักเจี้ยนคังแห่งนี้ไว้ได้
she will definitely return to my side.
นางจะต้องกลับมาอยู่ข้างกายข้าแน่นอน
[A few months later]
[หลายเดือนต่อมา]
[Beifu Army Barracks, Northern Border]
[ค่ายทหารทัพเป๋ยฝู่ แดนเหนือ]
How could I ever kill Xiuxiu?
ข้าจะฆ่าซิ่วซิ่วได้อย่างไร
I grew up with her.
ข้ากับนางโตมาด้วยกัน
I was waiting to save enough
ยังรอข้าเก็บเงินเดือนทหารให้ครบ
military pay to propose to her.
เพื่อไปสู่ขอนาง
[Guo Jiu, Beifu soldier]
[กัวจิ่ว ทหารเป๋ยฝู่]
How could I possibly kill her?
ข้าจะฆ่านางได้อย่างไร
I can't control myself.
ข้าควบคุมตัวเองไม่ได้
I want to kill people.
ข้าอยากฆ่าคน
I want to hack people.
ข้าอยากฟันคน
I want to bite people!
ข้าอยากกัดคน
I've been consumed by a curse.
ข้าถูกคำสาปเล่นงานแล้ว
Yes, a curse!
ใช่ คำสาป
This is a curse on the Beifu Army.
นี่คือคำสาปของทัพเป๋ยฝู่
Beifu shouldn't have reformed!
เป๋ยฝู่ไม่ควรปฏิรูป
God cast a curse.
คำสาปจากสวรรค์
This is retribution!
นี่คือกรรมตามสนอง
Including last night's incident,
รวมเมื่อคืนด้วย
there have been 9 cases
เกิดคดีทหาร
of soldiers going nuts and hurting people.
คลุ้มคลั่งทำร้ายคนแล้วเก้าคดี
Everyone says that
ชาวบ้านต่างพูดกันว่า
this curse is aimed at the Beifu Reform.
คำสาปนี้มุ่งเป้ามาที่การปฏิรูปเป๋ยฝู่
Nothing happens without a cause.
ทุกอย่างเกิดขึ้นย่อมมีสาเหตุ
Get Ruisheng over quickly.
รีบไปเรียกหรุ่ยเซิงมาเร็ว
This is the cause of the disease.
นี่คือสาเหตุของโรค
Stray dogs that eat this rice
หมาจรจัดที่กินข้าวเปลือกพวกนี้เข้าไป
will end up this way.
ก็มีอาการแบบนี้
Berserk, out of control, and bloodthirsty.
ก้าวร้าว เสียการควบคุม กระหายเลือด
The onset time varies.
ระยะเวลาการแสดงอาการต่างกัน
Some fall ill right after consuming it.
บางคนกินเข้าไปก็แสดงอาการทันที
Others take 3 to 5 days.
บางคนต้องรอสามถึงห้าวัน
It's the rations allocated by the imperial court from Guazhou.
เป็นเสบียงทหารที่ราชสำนักส่งมาจากกวาโจว
It's dark in color
สีออกเข้ม
but not moldy.
แต่ไม่ขึ้นรา
It looks like it was soaked in water.
เหมือนถูกแช่น้ำมาก่อน
I once saw it in one
ข้าเคยเห็นในตำราเล่มหนึ่งของเจียอวี๋
of Jiayu's books about mining methods.
บันทึกเกี่ยวกับวิธีการทำเหมืองแร่
Some people who drink water from the mines
มีบางคนที่ดื่มน้ำจากบนเขาเหมืองแร่
would fall into a coma and become delirious.
จะหมดสติและคลุ้มคลั่ง
Long-term consumption
หากดื่มเป็นเวลานาน
would greatly affect one's lifespan.
จะทำให้อายุสั้นลงมาก
Although what's happening now is not exactly the same,
ถึงสถานการณ์ตอนนี้ จะไม่เหมือนกันเสียทีเดียว
it's quite similar.
แต่ก็คล้ายกันมาก
But does Guazhou
แต่ที่กวาโจว
have any mines?
มีเหมืองแร่ด้วยหรือ
No, I guess? I haven't heard of any.
ไม่มีกระมัง ไม่เคยได้ยินว่ามีนะ
Guazhou.
กวาโจว
The Cui family.
ตระกูลชุย
It's time to investigate the Cui family
ตระกูลชุยของฮองเฮาเหวินซี
Empress Wenxi was born into.
ถึงเวลาที่ต้องไปตรวจสอบดูหน่อยแล้ว
By the way.
จริงสิ
Your cure.
ยาของท่านเจ้าค่ะ
Cure?
ยาหรือ
Ruisheng, is everything going well in the Northern Border?
พี่หญิงหรุ่ยเซิง ที่แดนเหนือทุกอย่างเรียบร้อยดีไหม
I heard winter is coming, so remember to wrap up warm.
ได้ยินว่าใกล้จะเข้าฤดูหนาวแล้ว อย่าลืมใส่เสื้อผ้าให้อบอุ่นนะ
My master and I improved the steelmaking method recently
ช่วงนี้ข้ากับอาจารย์ได้พัฒนาวิธีการทำเหล็ก
and forged a new set of medical needles for you.
เลยทำเข็มแพทย์ชุดใหม่ให้พี่หญิง
They should be thinner and tougher
น่าจะบางและทนทานกว่าชุดที่พี่หญิง
than those you usually use.
ใช้เป็นประจำ
I also made a mirror for Yuanji.
และทำคันฉ่องให้พี่หญิงหยวนจีบานหนึ่ง
It's not as good as a bronze one, though.
แต่ก็สู้คันฉ่องทองแดงไม่ได้
My master is determined to make caltrop fireballs.
อาจารย์มุ่งมั่นจะสร้างหนามอัคคี
I plan to leave Jiankang with him to look for ore.
ข้ากะว่าจะตามเขาออกจากเจี้ยนคังไปตามหาแร่
We'll go to Mount Tugao first, and then head southwest.
ไปเขาถูเกาก่อน จากนั้นค่อยไปทางตะวันตกเฉียงใต้
It's said to abound with bandits.
ได้ยินว่าที่นั่นโจรชุกชุมมาก
It's a good chance to test my lightness skill.
พอดีเลยจะได้ลองวิชาตัวเบาของข้า
She's messing around.
เหลวไหล
How heartless.
ใจร้าย
Do you think caltrop fireballs really exist?
ท่านว่า มีหนามอัคคีอยู่จริงไหม
[Outside of Lingfeng Fort, Guazhou]
[นอกป้อมหลิงเฟิง กวาโจว]
Could the things recorded in these ancient texts
ที่เขียนไว้ในตำราโบราณนี่
just be made up?
ล้วนเป็นเรื่องหลอกลวงหรือเปล่า
How could there be such a powerful ore?
จะมีแร่ที่ร้ายกาจขนาดนั้นได้อย่างไร
Once set aflame, it can't be extinguished by water,
ติดไฟโดนน้ำก็ไม่ดับ
blocking out the sun
บดบังฟ้าดิน
and leaving nothing alive.
ต้นหญ้าไม่ขึ้น
It definitely exists.
มันต้องมีจริงอยู่แล้ว
Well...
นี่
Please enjoy your meal.
เชิญทุกท่านกินตามสบาย
Thank you.
ขอบคุณ
If it didn't exist,
หากไม่มีจริง
why would the ancients record it in books?
คนโบราณจะเขียนไว้ในตำราทำไม
Would they just play a joke on us later generations?
ล้อเล่นกับคนรุ่นหลังอย่างพวกเราหรือไง
Besides,
อีกอย่างนะ
as vast as the world is,
ใต้หล้ากว้างใหญ่
how much of it have you actually seen?
เจ้าเคยเดินทางไปไกลแค่ไหนกันเชียว
Speaking of which,
หากพูดถึงการเดินทาง
I've traveled further and wider
ทางที่ข้าเคยเดิน
-than... -Than
- มากกว่าเจ้า... - มากกว่าสะพาน
my White ever has.
ที่เสี่ยวไป๋ที่บ้านเคยข้ามเสียอีก
Who is W-White?
เสี่ยว เสี่ยวไป๋เป็นใคร
Woof, woof.
โฮ่ง ๆ
Seriously,
เข้าเรื่องดีกว่า
are you sure your mother is in Lingfeng Fort?
เจ้าแน่ใจนะ ว่าแม่ของเจ้าอยู่ที่ป้อมหลิงเฟิงน่ะ
This is the fief of the Cuis,
ที่นี่มันบ้านเกิดของฮองเฮาเหวินซี
Empress Wenxi's maternal family.
ที่ดินศักดินาของตระกูลชุยนะ
-You old wretch, -Around here...
- ยายเฒ่าเอ๊ย - บริเวณนี้...
do you want to die?
เบื่อชีวิตแล้วใช่ไหม
Please don't.
อย่า
No monthly payment, no stall here!
ถ้าไม่จ่ายค่าคุ้มครอง ก็อย่าหวังว่าจะได้ตั้งแผงที่นี่
Hurry!
ให้ไว
In broad daylight...
กลางวันแสก ๆ
Take it out!
เอาออกมานะ
I really don't have any.
ข้าไม่มีจริง ๆ
Madam, are you okay?
ท่านยาย ท่านไม่เป็นไรนะ
I'm fine.
ข้าไม่เป็นไร ไม่เป็นไร
You caused trouble again.
ก่อเรื่องอีกแล้ว
Let's go! Run!
ไปเร็ว หนีเร็วเข้า
Hey, what's wrong with me fighting for justice?
เดี๋ยวนะ ข้าทำดีช่วยคนมันผิดตรงไหน
I don't want to do this either.
ข้าก็ไม่อยากทำเช่นนี้
I have no choice.
ข้าเองก็ไม่มีทางเลือก
You guys...
พวกเจ้า
Come on, smell it.
เร็ว ดม
Here, smell it.
มา ดมสิ
Let's go. Run quickly. Hurry!
ไป หนีเร็วเข้า ให้ไว
Who exactly are they after?
พวกเขาตามใครมากันแน่
Are they Northern Qin spies here to catch you?
คงไม่ใช่สายลับเป่ยฉินมาจับท่านหรอกนะ
Me?
ข้าหรือ
We agreed to go to Mount Tugao
ตกลงกันว่าจะไปเขาถูเกา
and only came here after receiving your mother's letter.
พอได้รับสารจากแม่ของเจ้าถึงได้มาที่นี่
Who do you think they are after?
เจ้าว่าตามใครมากันล่ะ
Hurry! Let's go!
เร็วเข้า ๆ
Mother...
ท่านแม่
My mother is in danger.
ท่านแม่ข้าตกอยู่ในอันตราย
Nanxing, hurry.
หนานซิง เร็วเข้า
Go find Xiao Wuyi immediately. Hurry.
เจ้ารีบไปหาเซียวอู๋อี เร็ว
My Lady, I'm going then.
คุณหนู งั้นข้าไปก่อนนะ
Quickly!
ให้ไวเลย
Let's go. We should run now. Hurry!
ไป ๆ ๆ รีบหนีเร็วเข้า
[Cui Shi]
[ชุยสือ]
I...
ข้า
Take them away.
เอาตัวไป
[Lingfeng Fort]
[ป้อมหลิงเฟิง]
Young Master.
คุณชาย
The Young Lady still refuses to try on the wedding dress.
คุณหนูยังไม่ยอมลองชุดแต่งงานเจ้าค่ะ
[Cui Shao'an]
[ชุยเส้าอัน]
You may leave.
ออกไป
Foot.
เท้า
The other one.
อีกข้าง
[Cui Lingyi]
[ชุยลิ่งอี๋]
Do you really plan to stay in the Cui family's place forever?
คิดจะเกาะตระกูลชุยไปตลอดชีวิตจริง ๆ หรือไง
This is Cui Mansion,
ที่นี่คือบ้านตระกูลชุย
my home.
เป็นบ้านของข้า
If you have a share, I should have one as well.
มีส่วนของเจ้าก็มีส่วนของข้าด้วย
What do you mean?
แล้วท่านจะเอายังไง
Do you insist on finding a matrilocal husband?
จะแต่งเขยเข้าบ้านให้ได้งั้นหรือ
Cui Shao'an,
ชุยเส้าอัน
all you want is to drive me
เจ้าก็แค่อยากจะไล่ข้า
out of the Cui Mansion,
ออกไปจากตระกูลชุย
so you can hold sway over the entire Cui family.
จากนั้นเจ้าจะได้ควบคุมตระกูลชุยทั้งหมด
Since childhood,
ตั้งแต่เล็กจนโต
be it studying or managing affairs,
ไม่ว่าจะเรื่องงานหรือเรื่องเรียน
you're nowhere near as good as me.
มีเรื่องไหนที่เจ้าสู้ข้าได้บ้าง
We are both Father's children.
ต่างเป็นลูกของท่านพ่อเหมือนกัน
Why are you the Young Master?
เจ้ามีสิทธิ์อะไรได้เป็นนายน้อย
Lingyi,
พี่หญิง
you are already going to marry Prince Qi.
ท่านกำลังจะแต่งงานกับฉีอ๋องแล้ว
What else are you dissatisfied with?
ยังมีอะไรไม่พอใจอีก
What's there about
ตระกูลชุย
the Cui family that you're holding onto?
มีอะไรให้ท่านต้องอาลัยอาวรณ์หรือ
There is nothing worth holding onto.
ไม่มีอะไรให้น่าอาลัยอาวรณ์หรอก
I just don't want you
ข้าก็แค่กลัวว่าตระกูลชุย
to ruin the Cui family.
จะพังพินาศด้วยน้ำมือของเจ้าแค่นั้นเอง
Young Master.
คุณชาย
We have caught the person.
จับคนมาได้แล้วขอรับ
Cui Shao'an, who did you catch this time?
ชุยเส้าอัน เจ้าไปจับใครมาอีก
A beauty, of course.
ก็ต้องเป็นสาวงามอยู่แล้ว
Cui Lingyi, the imperial edict for your marriage has been issued.
ชุยลิ่งอี๋ ราชโองการสมรสพระราชทานลงมาแล้ว
You have to leave whether you want to or not.
ท่านไม่อยากไปก็ต้องไป
Where is she?
ไหนล่ะ
She definitely hasn't run out of Lingfeng Fort.
จะต้องหนีออกจากป้อมหลิงเฟิงไปไม่ได้แน่ ๆ
I'll lead our men to search immediately.
ข้าจะรีบนำคนไปค้นหาเดี๋ยวนี้ขอรับ
Go!
ไป
Where did Yuan Xiaoliu go?
หยวนเสี่ยวลิ่วไปไหนแล้วนะ
Follow me out of the Fort!
ตามข้าออกจากป้อม
Search the entire Guazhou
ในเขตกวาโจว
for her!
ต้องหานางเจอให้ได้
Don't look so gloomy.
พวกเจ้าแต่ละคนอย่ามาทำหน้าเศร้า
Since you are already here,
ในเมื่อมาถึงที่นี่แล้ว
just settle down.
ก็ทำใจให้สบาย
In the future,
ต่อไป
you will all enjoy lives of wealth and privileges.
พวกเจ้าจะได้เสพสุขบนกองเงินกองทองเชียวนะ
So be smart, all of you.
พวกเจ้าแต่ละคนฉลาดกันหน่อย
Being chosen to serve the Young Master
ได้รับเลือกให้รับใช้คุณชาย
is your blessing.
ถือเป็นวาสนาของพวกเจ้า
Cheer up, everyone!
มีชีวิตชีวากันหน่อย
Stop pulling a long face!
อย่ามาทำหน้าอมทุกข์
You'll be the one.
เจ้าแล้วกัน
So useless!
ไม่ได้เรื่อง
Why did she faint from fright?
ทำไมนางถึงตกใจจนเป็นลมไปล่ะ
It's said that those chosen by the Young Master will suffer greatly.
ได้ยินว่าถ้าถูกคุณชายเลือก จะโดนทรมานสารพัด
But working in the mines in the back mountain is different.
แต่หากไปทำงานเหมืองที่อยู่หลังเขา ก็จะแตกต่างออกไป
Lingfeng Fort provides food and clothes.
ทั้งการกินการอยู่ก็จะอยู่ในป้อมหลิงเฟิงหมด
And there's even a monthly allowance to send to our families.
แต่ละเดือนยังมีเงินเดือนให้ครอบครัวอีกด้วย
Lingfeng Fort is indeed running illegal private mines.
ป้อมหลิงเฟิงลักลอบเปิดเหมืองแร่จริงด้วย
Are all these girls going to work in the mines?
หรือว่าสตรีพวกนี้ล้วนไปขุดแร่กัน
But why choose girls?
ทำไมต้องเลือกสตรีด้วย
Could Mother also be there?
ท่านแม่ข้าจะอยู่ที่นั่นด้วยไหมน้า
Why the long face?
ทำหน้าเศร้าทำไม
You'll be the one.
เจ้าแล้วกัน
Take the rest of them to the workshop.
ส่งคนอื่นไปยังโรงผลิตให้หมด
Young Master,
คุณชาย
she's the prettiest among this batch of girls.
นางเป็นสตรีที่หน้าตางดงามที่สุดในกลุ่มนี้
I was just about to take her to your room.
บ่าวกำลังเตรียมจะส่งนาง ไปที่ห้องของท่านพอดีเลยเจ้าค่ะ
Turn your head this way.
หันหน้ามาสิ
She is not much to look at,
ขี้เหร่ไปหน่อยนะ
but I'll take her.
นางแล้วกัน
Take her to my room.
ส่งนางไปที่ห้องข้า
Understood.
เจ้าค่ะ
I'm Yang Zhang, the County Sheriff. Greetings, Your Highness.
นายอำเภอหยางจาง คารวะซื่อจื่อ
[Hall of the County Sheriff's Mansion, Guazhou]
[ห้องโถงจวนนายอำเภอ กวาโจว]
What brings you to Guazhou, Your Highness?
ทำไมซื่อจื่อมาที่กวาโจวล่ะ
Is it official business?
มีงานราชการหรือ
Weird illnesses have been breaking out across Guazhou,
กวาโจวเกิดโรคประหลาดขึ้นบ่อยครั้ง
yet you didn't report to the Imperial Medical Bureau.
แต่เจ้ากลับไม่รายงานต่อสำนักแพทย์หลวง
Instead, you murdered witnesses and destroyed corpses.
ฆ่าคนปิดปาก ทำลายศพเพื่ออำพราง
[Yang Zhang, Guazhou County Sheriff]
[หยางจาง นายอำเภอกวาโจว]
Yang Zhang,
หยางจาง
if I were on official business here,
หากข้ามาเพราะงานราชการ
you would've already been executed.
หัวของเจ้าคงหลุดจากบ่าไปตั้งนานแล้ว
I have no idea.
ข้าน้อยไม่ทราบ
I really don't know.
ไม่ทราบจริง ๆ นะขอรับ
How long are you going to keep covering for the Cuis?
เจ้าจะปิดบังตระกูลชุยไปถึงเมื่อไหร่
I really have no idea!
ข้าน้อยไม่ทราบจริง ๆ นะ
I'm only making a guess.
ข้าน้อยก็แค่คาดเดาเท่านั้น
The Cui family is Empress Wenxi's maternal family,
ตระกูลชุยเป็นสกุลฝั่งพระมารดา ของฮองเฮาเหวินซี
the top noble family in Ye,
เป็นตระกูลอันดับหนึ่งของต้าเย่
with deep roots.
รากฐานมั่นคง
I'm merely a lowly County Sheriff.
ข้าเป็นเพียงนายอำเภอตัวเล็ก ๆ
Where did the disease originate?
ต้นตอของเชื้อโรคมาจากที่ใด
Lingfeng Fort.
ป้อมหลิงเฟิงขอรับ
The Cui family's granary is located right in Lingfeng Fort.
ฉางข้าวของตระกูลชุยอยู่ในป้อมหลิงเฟิง
The mines are also in Lingfeng Fort.
เหมืองแร่ก็อยู่ในป้อมหลิงเฟิงด้วย
Since the Cui family is Empress Wenxi's maternal family,
ในเมื่อตระกูลชุยเป็นสกุลฝั่งพระมารดา ของฮองเฮาเหวินซี
when you took me to flee back then,
ตอนนั้นที่ท่านพาข้าหนี
why did you seek help from the Xiaos
เหตุใดถึงไม่ไปหาตระกูลชุย
instead of turning to the Cuis?
แต่กลับไปขอความช่วยเหลือจากตระกูลเซียวเล่า
Why have you even hidden my existence
หลายปีมานี้ ถึงกับปิดบังตระกูลชุย
from the Cui family over these years?
เรื่องการมีอยู่ของข้า
Empress Wenxi was forced into it.
ฮองเฮาทรงถูกบีบบังคับน่ะ
She had just given birth
ตอนนั้นพระนางเพิ่งพระประสูติกาลใหม่ ๆ
when she heard of His Majesty's death.
ก็ทราบข่าวว่าฝ่าบาทสิ้นพระชนม์ในสนามรบ
But she didn't intend to give up the Capital.
แต่พระนางก็ไม่คิดจะทอดทิ้งเมืองหลวง
The noble families
ตระกูลใหญ่หลายตระกูล
deliberately delayed sending troops.
จงใจถ่วงเวลาไม่ยอมส่งทหารสักที
When the army reached the city gates,
เมื่อเห็นกองทัพศัตรูมาประชิดเมือง
Cui Jun submitted a secret memorial,
ตอนนี้ชุยจวิ้นจึงถวายฎีกาลับ
hoping that the Empress would sacrifice her own family
ขอให้ฮองเฮาทรงเห็นแก่ส่วนรวม
for the bigger picture.
สละครอบครัว
What bigger picture?
ส่วนรวมแบบไหน
To win over the noble families,
เพื่อเอาใจเหล่าตระกูลขุนนางใหญ่
she had to dispatch the remaining Imperial Guards
เลยต้องใช้ทหารรักษาพระองค์ที่เหลืออยู่
to escort these noble families as they fled south.
คุ้มครองตระกูลขุนนางเหล่านี้อพยพลงใต้
The Empress was left alone,
เหลือเพียงฮองเฮาพระองค์เดียว
with His Majesty's child,
พร้อมด้วยพระโอรสของฝ่าบาท
defending the Capital by herself.
ปกป้องเมืองหลวงตามลำพัง
The nobles abandoned the Empress
ลูกหลานตระกูลขุนนางใหญ่ทอดทิ้งฮองเฮา
to save the Ye Empire.
ให้รักษาแผ่นดินต้าเย่ลำพัง
From then on,
นับแต่นั้นมา
the Cui family rose to become the head of the noble families.
ตระกูลชุยก็กลายเป็นผู้นำ ของตระกูลขุนนางใหญ่
Your mother, Empress Wenxi,
ฮองเฮาเหวินซี พระมารดาของท่าน
died at that time.
ก็สิ้นพระชนม์ลงในตอนนั้น
Qing Long,
ชิงหลง
report the news about Guazhou to Jiankang immediately
รีบรายงานเรื่องในกวาโจวให้เจี้ยนคังทราบ
and send a secret letter to the Eastern Palace—
แล้วส่งสารลับไปยังตำหนักบูรพา
the Cui family is suspicious,
ตระกูลชุยมีท่าทีแปลกไป
and the marriage needs to be reconsidered.
เรื่องงานแต่งต้องพิจารณาใหม่
Find an excuse to put it off.
หาข้ออ้างถ่วงเวลาไว้ก่อน
Understood.
ขอรับ
Nanxing?
หนานซิง
Your Highness,
ซื่อจื่อ
please save our Young Lady.
ท่านรีบช่วยคุณหนูของพวกเราด้วยเถอะ
The Cui family tricked her into coming here
นางถูกคนตระกูลชุยหลอกมาที่นี่
and caught her.
ถูกพวกเขาจับตัวไปแล้ว
Weren't she and Yuan Xiaoliu supposed to go to Mount Tugao?
นางกับหยวนเสี่ยวลิ่วจะไปเขาถูเกามิใช่หรือ
Why did they end up in Guazhou?
ไฉนมาอยู่ที่กวาโจวได้
That was the original plan.
ตอนแรกก็เป็นแบบนั้น
But Her Ladyship received a letter from the Princess.
แต่คุณหนูได้รับสารจากท่านหญิง
The Princess said
ท่านหญิงบอกว่า
there were black-radiance ores here that she once looked for
ที่นี่มีแร่นิลหลากสี ที่คุณหนูเคยต้องการตามหา
and invited her to take a look.
เลยชวนคุณหนูมาดู
Yet she fell into a trap
ใครจะไปรู้ว่าพอมาถึงที่นี่
after arriving here.
ก็ตกหลุมพรางแล้ว
What did the Cuis capture Xie Jiayu for?
ตระกูลชุยจับเซี่ยเจียอวี๋ไปทำไม
The Cuis not only run illegal mines
ตระกูลชุยไม่เพียงลักลอบเปิดเหมือง
but also kidnapped the Princess and Xie Jiayu.
ยังจับตัวท่านหญิงกับเซี่ยเจียอวี๋ไปอีก
They must be up to something else.
ต้องมีแผนการอื่นแน่
You two get ready and follow me
พวกเจ้าสองคนไปเตรียมตัวหน่อย
into Lingfeng Fortress right away.
แล้วตามข้าเข้าป้อมหลิงเฟิงทันที
Your Highness, you must be careful.
ซื่อจื่อ โปรดรอบคอบด้วย
The nobles' forts are always heavily guarded.
ป้อมใต้ดินของตระกูลขุนนางใหญ่ มีการป้องกันอย่างแน่นหนามาแต่ไหนแต่ไร
How will we get in?
จะเข้าไปยังไง
We'll walk in aboveboard.
เข้าไปอย่างเปิดเผยนี่แหละ
What's your name?
ชื่ออะไร
My name is...
ข้าชื่อ...
Forget it.
ช่างเถอะ
It doesn't matter what your name used to be.
ก่อนหน้านี้เจ้าชื่ออะไรไม่สำคัญ
From today on,
ตั้งแต่วันนี้ไป
you'll be called
ให้เจ้าชื่อว่า
Yueniang.
เยว่เหนียงแล้วกัน
Singing, dancing, or whatever—
ความสามารถด้านการร้องรำอะไรพวกนั้น
just show me something.
แสดงมาสักอย่างสิ
I don't know how.
ไม่เป็น
I've always hated composing poetry or couplets
ชีวิตนี้ข้าเกลียดการแต่งกลอนตอบโคลง
just to put on airs.
แบบอวดภูมิที่สุด
And I abhor "Admonitions for Women" even more.
ยิ่งหลักธรรมคำสอนกุลสตรียิ่งเกลียดเข้าไส้
How about...
ไม่งั้น
I do a magic trick for you?
ข้าแสดงกลให้ท่านดูแล้วกัน
I've never seen any woman,
ข้ายังไม่เคยเห็นแม่นางคนไหน
no, anyone,
ไม่สิ ไม่เคยเห็นใคร
solve the Nine-Linked Rings faster than you.
ที่แก้ห่วงเก้าวงได้เร็วกว่าเจ้าเลยนะ
It's nothing.
นี่ยังไม่เท่าไรนะ
I know a lot more.
ข้าทำได้เยอะแยะเลยละ
If you have anything else you want me to solve,
หากท่านยังมีอะไรที่อยากให้ข้าแก้อีก
just bring it on.
เอามาได้เลย
You're so much better than those noble ladies.
เจ้าเก่งกว่าพวกคุณหนูตระกูลผู้ดีเยอะเลย
When I send you to the imperial palace,
ถึงตอนนั้นส่งเจ้าเข้าวัง
you can compete with my sister.
จะได้ไปประชันกับพี่หญิงของข้าด้วย
Hold on, hold on... The imperial palace?
เดี๋ยวนะเดี๋ยว เข้าวังหรือ
You want me to go to the imperial palace with your sister?
ท่านให้ข้าเข้าวังพร้อมกับพี่หญิงของท่าน
Aren't you hurting her this way?
นี่ท่านไม่ใช่ กำลังทำร้ายพี่หญิงของท่านอยู่หรือ
It's her own fault for always going against me.
ใครใช้ให้นางขัดใจข้าทุกเรื่องล่ะ
She has to meddle in everything I do.
ควบคุมข้าทุกเรื่อง
It's nice to have someone care about what you do.
มีคนคอยดูแลก็ดีนี่นา
Unlike me, no one keeps me in check.
อย่างข้าไม่มีใครดูแล
I have suffered so much in my life.
ชีวิตของข้าลำบากมากเลย
Given your status,
ด้วยสถานะของเจ้า
who would dare to make you suffer?
ใครกล้าปล่อยให้เจ้าลำบากกัน
Pardon?
อะไรนะ
Do you know, in these troubled times,
เจ้ารู้ไหมในใต้หล้าที่วุ่นวายนี้
how much money it costs to maintain
การจะบำรุงเส้นผมให้ดำสลวยเช่นเจ้าได้
such beautiful black hair like yours?
ต้องใช้เงินทองมากมายเท่าไร
It symbolizes a life of abundance only someone who's never
นี่มันบุตรีที่ถูกเลี้ยงดูมาอย่างสุขสบาย
suffered from cold or hunger could live.
บนกองเงินกองทอง
You're a girl raised in wealth and luxury.
โดยไม่เคยผ่านความลำบากมาเลยนะ
Yet our Lingfeng Fortress only takes in refugee girls,
และป้อมหลิงเฟิงของข้า รับแต่ผู้ลี้ภัยกับเด็กกำพร้า
who know nothing about singing, dancing, or Nine-Linked Rings.
จะร้องรำแก้ห่วงเก้าวงได้อย่างไร
They can't even afford food.
ข้าวยังไม่มีจะกินเลย
Someone as versatile
คนที่มีความสามารถรอบด้าน
and healthy as you
แถมยังดูอวบอิ่มมีน้ำมีนวลเยี่ยงเจ้า
is the first we've ever had.
เป็นคนแรกเลยนะ
Tell me.
บอกมา
Who are you?
เจ้าเป็นใคร
I...
ข้า
I'm indeed not a refugee.
ข้าไม่ใช่ผู้ลี้ภัยจริง ๆ
I am...
ข้าคือ
C-Come closer.
มา มานี่
I am the envoy from the Eastern Palace,
ข้าน้อยอาต้า ทหารรักษาพระองค์ฝ่ายขวา
Da, the Right Imperial Guard.
ทูตจากตำหนักบูรพา
Greetings, Prince Qi's Consort.
คารวะพระชายาฉีอ๋อง
I'm not married yet.
ยังไม่ได้แต่งงาน
You can just call me Lady Cui.
เรียกแม่นางชุยก็พอ
Lady Cui,
แม่นางชุย
these are
ของพวกนี้
all gifts from His Highness.
ล้วนเป็นของขวัญที่ท่านอ๋องมอบให้
Hope they are to your liking.
หวังว่าจะถูกใจแม่นาง
There's no trace of Lady Xie.
ไม่พบร่องรอยของแม่นางเซี่ย
I haven't found her either,
ข้าก็ไม่พบขอรับ
nor have I found the dungeon.
และก็ไม่พบคุกใต้ดินด้วย
The new concubine the Young Master took
อนุภรรยาคนใหม่ที่คุณชายรับเข้ามา
is way too demanding.
ก็ช่างเรื่องมากจริง ๆ
She even asked us to split a bamboo
ยังจะให้พวกเราเอาไม้ไผ่หนึ่งลำ
into 100 bamboo strips.
มาผ่าเป็นเส้นเล็ก ๆ ร้อยเส้น
She's clearly just torturing us.
นี่มันแกล้งกันชัด ๆ
What water filtering?
กรองน้ำอะไรกัน
I think she's just fooling the Young Master.
ข้าว่าหลอกคุณชายมากกว่า
You continue to investigate the defenses in Lingfeng Fort.
พวกเจ้าสำรวจการป้องกันในป้อมหลิงเฟิงต่อไป
Here are the things you asked for.
ส่งของมาแล้วเจ้าค่ะ
Where should we put them?
จะให้วางไว้ตรงไหนเจ้าคะ
Just put them anywhere here.
พวกเจ้าวางตรงนี้ก็ได้
You...
ท่าน
It's me.
ข้าเอง
I know it's you.
ข้ารู้ว่าเป็นท่าน
How did you know I came to Lingfeng Fort?
เจ้ารู้ได้อย่างไร ว่าข้ามาที่ป้อมหลิงเฟิงแล้ว
The Eastern Palace's envoy, Da, who can speak.
อาต้า ทูตจากตำหนักบูรพา แถมพูดได้ด้วย
Who else could it be but you?
นอกจากท่านแล้วจะเป็นใครได้อีกล่ะ
But I didn't expect
แต่ข้าคิดไม่ถึงว่า
you to be here so soon.
ท่านจะมาเร็วขนาดนี้
It should take at least 6 or 7 days
จากที่นี่ไปเป๋ยฝู่
to get here from Beifu, right?
ยังไงก็ต้องใช้เวลาหกเจ็ดวันหรือเปล่า
A strange disease broke out in Beifu,
เป๋ยฝู่เกิดโรคประหลาดขึ้น
and it's related to Guazhou.
เกี่ยวข้องกับกวาโจว
I ran into Nanxing
วันแรกที่ข้ามาถึงที่นี่
on my first day here.
ก็เจอกับหนานซิง
She said you asked her to find me.
นางบอกว่าเจ้าให้นางมาหาข้า
I'm really lucky.
ข้าโชคดีจริง ๆ
You're already locked up here.
ถูกจับมาถึงที่นี่แล้ว
How can you call that "lucky"?
เจ้ายังจะบอกว่าโชคดีอีก
I...
ข้า
How did you manage to fool Cui Shao'an?
เจ้าหลอกชุยเส้าอันยังไง
Actually,
ที่จริง
I didn't succeed at first.
ตอนแรกก็หลอกไม่ได้หรอก
Since you've found out about it,
ในเมื่อถูกท่านจับได้แล้ว
I'll just be honest with you.
งั้นข้าจะพูดกับท่านตรง ๆ เลยนะ
Have you ever heard about
ท่านเคยได้ยินไหม
the position of Tomb-excavating General established by Cao Bao?
ในอดีตสมัยเฉาเว่ย มีการแต่งตั้งตำแหน่งแม่ทัพขุดสุสาน
We are all descendants of the Tomb Raiders.
พวกข้าล้วนเป็นทายาทของนายทหารขุดสุสาน
I am the 6th-generation successor
ทายาทนายทหารขุดสุสานรุ่นที่หก
of Tomb Raiders.
ก็คือข้าเอง
You don't believe me?
ท่านไม่เชื่อหรือ
You wouldn't want us to "visit"
ท่านเองก็คงไม่อยากให้สุสานตระกูลชุย
the Cui family's graves, would you?
ถูกพวกข้าไปเยี่ยมเยียนใช่ไหมล่ะ
Your grandfather's,
ของท่านปู่ท่าน
your father's,
ของท่านพ่อท่าน
or yours?
หรือว่าของท่าน
You know what?
ข้าจะบอกท่านให้นะ
We Tomb Raiders
นักขุดสุสานอย่างพวกข้าน่ะ
have nothing
สิ่งอื่นไม่มี
but patience.
มีแต่ความอดทน
I can wait for a few decades,
ต่อไปข้าจะรอแปดสิบปีร้อยปี
you know,
ข้าจะบอกท่านให้นะ
and I'll dig up your entire family's tombs.
ข้าจะขุดสุสานตระกูลท่านให้หมด
-All of them... -Enough.
- ทั้งหมดจะ... - หยุด
Little girl,
สาวน้อย
do you think I'm stupid?
เจ้าคิดว่าข้าโง่หรือไง
F-Fine, alright.
ก็ได้ ๆ ๆ
I admit that
ข้ายอมรับ
I saw your family running illegal private mines.
ข้าเห็นพวกท่านลักลอบเปิดเหมืองแร่
But I know the rules of the trade.
แต่กฎของวงการนี้ข้าเข้าใจดี
I won't say a single word
เรื่องที่ไม่ควรพูด
about what I shouldn't reveal.
ข้าจะไม่แพร่งพรายออกไปแม้แต่คำเดียว
But we tomb raiders
แต่ท่านก็รู้สายขุดสุสานอย่างพวกข้า
want a share of what we see,
ใครพบเห็นก็ต้องมีส่วนแบ่งด้วย
you know?
ใช่ไหมล่ะ
Why do you still not believe me?
ทำไมท่านยังไม่เชื่อข้าอีกล่ะ
I...
ข้า
Has anyone fainted
ที่เหมืองของพวกท่าน
or become berserk or manic all of a sudden
ช่วงนี้มีคนเป็นลมหมดสติ
in your family's mines recently?
อารมณ์ฉุนเฉียว หรือคลุ้มคลั่งบ้างไหม
How did you know about it?
เจ้ารู้ได้อย่างไร
I know a lot.
เรื่องที่ข้ารู้เยอะแยะเลยละ
It's because of the water.
ปัญหาน้ำ
Do you want to solve it?
ท่านอยากจะแก้ไขไหม
I can help you.
ข้าช่วยท่านได้นะ
And the "concubine"?
อนุภรรยาล่ะ
What's that about?
มันยังไงกัน
It's nothing but an excuse.
ก็แค่ข้ออ้างเฉย ๆ
I promised to help him filter water.
ข้ารับปากว่าจะช่วยเขาสร้างการกรองน้ำ
So I could stall until you came here, right?
จะได้ถ่วงเวลาให้ท่านมาทันได้ไง
Did you
เจ้า
send Nanxing to find me?
ให้หนานซิงมาหาข้าหรือ
Didn't I already tell you that?
เมื่อครู่ข้าพูดไปแล้วรอบหนึ่งไม่ใช่หรือ
Why?
ทำไมล่ะ
This place is clearly closer to Jiankang.
ที่นี่อยู่ใกล้เจี้ยนคังมากกว่าเห็น ๆ
Because you can use martial arts.
ก็ท่านมีวรยุทธ์ไม่ใช่หรือไง
What's wrong, Xiao Wuyi?
ท่านเป็นอะไรไป เซียวอู๋อี
It's debilitating powder.
ยาสลายกำลัง
Xiao Wuyi, stop joking around.
เซียวอู๋อี ท่านอย่าล้อเล่นน่า
If you're affected,
ท่านจะโดนยาได้ยังไง
why am I... Why am I perfectly fine?
แล้วข้า ทำไมข้าไม่เป็นอะไรเลยล่ะ
You can't use martial arts,
เจ้าไม่มีวรยุทธ์สักหน่อย
so of course you don't feel anything.
ย่อมไม่รู้สึกอะไรอยู่แล้ว
Just as expected,
ตามคาด
you know each other.
พวกเจ้ารู้จักกัน
Do you really think I believed
เจ้าคงไม่ได้คิดหรอกนะ ว่าเรื่องที่เจ้าพล่ามให้ข้าฟัง
all that nonsense you told me?
ข้าจะเชื่อจริง ๆ น่ะ
I just wanted to see
ข้าก็แค่อยากดู
what tricks you were going to play.
ว่าเจ้าจะเล่นลูกไม้อะไรกันแน่
But I have to admit that
แต่จะว่าไป
I was indeed interested in the water filter
การกรองน้ำที่เจ้าพูดถึงนั่น
you talked about.
ข้าสนใจจริง ๆ นะ
I swear I didn't lie to you about that.
เรื่องนี้ข้าไม่ได้โกหกท่านจริง ๆ
-I can really make the filter... -Hold on.
- การกรองน้ำนี่ข้าทำได้จริง ๆ - เดี๋ยวนะ
One at a time.
ทีละคน
Let's start with this one.
ท่านนี้ก่อน
Impersonating an envoy from the Eastern Palace,
แอบอ้างเป็นทูตจากตำหนักบูรพา
you must have an extraordinary identity.
ฐานะต้องไม่ธรรมดาแน่
How should I address you?
สหาย มีนามว่าอะไร
Xiao Wuyi.
เซียวอู๋อี
I've heard a lot about you.
ได้ยินชื่อเสียงมานาน
Oh, no.
แย่แล้ว
This is bad. This is really bad.
แย่แล้ว ๆ ๆ
Even the Beifu Army has been alerted.
สะเทือนไปถึงทัพเป๋ยฝู่แล้ว
Well...
งั้น
Then wouldn't the secret
งั้นความลับของป้อมหลิงเฟิง
about Lingfeng Fort be exposed?
ก็เก็บไว้ไม่อยู่แล้วน่ะสิ
So there's no other way.
งั้นก็ช่วยไม่ได้แล้ว
I can only silence you.
คงต้องฆ่าปิดปาก
I...
ข้า
Why is he so talkative?
ทำไมเขาพูดมากขนาดนี้ล่ะ
That's why I sealed his mouth.
ก็เลยปิดปากเขาไว้ไง
He can't move his body either?
ร่างกายของเขาก็ขยับไม่ได้แล้วหรือ
I learned this from Ruisheng.
นี่ข้าเรียนมาจากพี่หญิงหรุ่ยเซิงน่ะ
I have sealed off all his meridians.
สกัดจุดเส้นลมปราณของเขาไว้
Now, he's basically frozen
ตอนนี้เขานอกจากตาที่ขยับได้
except for his eyes being able to move.
ส่วนอื่นขยับไม่ได้เลย
Awesome.
เก่งกาจ
How long have you learned it from Ruisheng?
เจ้าเรียนกับหรุ่ยเซิงมานานแค่ไหนล่ะ
This is my first time doing it.
แทงครั้งแรกน่ะ
I only watched it once.
ข้าเคยดูแค่ครั้งเดียวกระมัง
If I inserted it incorrectly,
นี่ถ้าเกิดว่าแทงผิดตำแหน่งไปนะ
he could be paralyzed.
อาจจะเป็นอัมพาตได้เลย
What now? I'm leaving.
ตอนนี้จะทำยังไงดี ข้าเผ่นก่อนนะ
Hold on.
ช้าก่อน
Do you know where the Lingfeng Fort's mines are?
เจ้ารู้ไหมว่า เหมืองแร่ของป้อมหลิงเฟิงอยู่ที่ไหน
In the back mountain.
หลังเขา
But for some reason,
แต่ไม่รู้ว่าทำไม
all the miners they recruit here are girls.
คนงานเหมืองที่นี่ถึงรับแต่สตรี
Statistics of refugees everywhere only count adult males.
การนับจำนวนผู้ลี้ภัยตามที่ต่าง ๆ จะนับแค่ผู้ชายที่บรรลุนิติภาวะ
Girls
สตรี
can be very deceptive.
หลอกสายตาคนอื่นได้ดี
Yeah.
จริงด้วย
At worst, he'd only be known
อย่างมากก็แค่ถูกมองว่า
as a lecherous Young Master of the Cui family.
เป็นคุณชายตระกูลชุยที่ลามก
How long will this acupuncture last?
เข็มของเจ้าอยู่ได้นานแค่ไหน
No idea.
ไม่รู้สิ
But when Ruisheng did it,
แต่ตอนที่ข้าเห็นพี่หญิงหรุ่ยเซิงแทง
that chicken lay there all day.
ไก่ตัวนั้นนอนนิ่งไปทั้งวันเลยนะ
Then we'll leave it to his fate.
งั้นก็คงสุดแล้วแต่โชคชะตาของเขาแล้วละ
Let's go.
ไป
Are you okay?
ไม่เป็นไรใช่ไหม
Who is holding up whom?
ตกลงใครพยุงใครกันแน่
My bad. I'll hold you up.
ข้าผิดเอง ข้าพยุงท่านเอง ๆ
Let's go.
ไป ๆ ๆ
Don't be afraid.
ไม่ต้องกลัว
Mining can cause deaths,
การทำเหมืองมีคนตายเป็นเรื่องปกติ
but how could so many people end up dead?
แต่ทำไมถึงมีคนตายเยอะขนาดนี้ล่ะ
After the Beifu soldiers ate
ทหารเป๋ยฝู่
the rice soaked in the mine water,
กินข้าวที่แช่น้ำจากเหมืองเข้าไป
they instantly went mad, lost their minds,
จะเกิดอาการคลุ้มคลั่งและเสียสติในทันที
and wanted to hurt people like beasts.
อยากจะทำร้ายคนเหมือนกับสัตว์ป่า
The mine water does make people go mad and lose their minds,
น้ำจากเหมือง ทำให้คนคลุ้มคลั่งเสียสติได้จริง
but this is the first time I've seen it lead to violence.
แต่ว่าทำร้ายคนข้าเพิ่งเห็นเป็นครั้งแรก
This is no ordinary iron ore.
เหมืองนี้ไม่ใช่เหมืองแร่เหล็กธรรมดา
Let's get out of Lingfeng Fort first.
ออกจากป้อมหลิงเฟิงก่อนแล้วค่อยว่ากัน
Let me help you. Let's go.
ข้าพยุงท่าน ไป
Where are you going, General?
นี่แม่ทัพจะไปที่ไหนหรือ
Lady Cui?
คุณหนูชุย
So she is Mao's future wife.
ที่แท้นางคือว่าที่ภรรยาของอาเม่านี่เอง
Fly, come on.
เหาะสิ เร็วเข้า
I'm ready.
ข้าพร้อมแล้ว
The drug hasn't worn off yet. I can't fly.
ฤทธิ์ยายังไม่หมดเลย มันเหาะไม่ได้
You two, would you like to come back with me for a chat?
ทั้งสองท่าน กลับไปคุยกับข้าหน่อยสิ
Brother, I think this robe is better.
ท่านพี่ ข้าว่าชุดนี้ดูดีนะ
That one is a bit too ornate
ชุดนั้นดูซับซ้อนเกินไป
and lacks elegance.
ทำให้ดูไม่สง่า
You decide.
เจ้าตัดสินใจเลย
Brother,
ท่านพี่
you usually like to wear
ปกติท่านชอบใส่
light-colored clothes,
เสื้อผ้าสีอ่อน
but I think you look better in dark red.
แต่ข้าว่าท่านใส่สีแดงเข้มจะดูดีกว่านะ
It gives you a more dignified air.
ดูสง่ากว่า
Either is fine.
ได้หมด
Brother, my sister-in-law is about to enter the imperial palace.
ท่านพี่ พี่สะใภ้ใกล้จะเข้าวังมาแล้วนะ
You need to prepare early.
ท่านต้องเตรียมตัวแต่เนิ่น ๆ นะ
Brother,
ท่านพี่
I know you are unwilling to accept it,
ข้ารู้ว่าท่านไม่เต็มใจ
but if the marriage alliance goes wrong,
แต่หากการเชื่อมสัมพันธ์ของสองตระกูล ไม่ราบรื่น
it will backfire.
จะทำให้สถานการณ์เลวร้ายลงนะ
I know you're worried about me.
รู้ว่าเจ้าเป็นห่วงข้า
You don't need to worry.
เจ้าไม่ต้องเป็นห่วงหรอก
You should care about your own affairs.
ห่วงเรื่องของเจ้าเองเถอะ
What about your marriage?
เรื่องแต่งงานของเจ้าล่ะ
Me?
ข้าหรือ
I won't marry anyone.
ข้าไม่แต่งงานหรอก
I just want to stay by your side.
ข้าอยู่ดูแลท่านก็พอแล้ว
Nonsense.
เหลวไหล
-Master. -Grand Tutor.
- อาจารย์ - ราชครู
Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋อง
You may leave.
พวกเจ้าออกไปก่อนเถอะ
Understood.
ขอรับ
Master.
อาจารย์
Your Highness, are you trying on the wedding attire?
ท่านอ๋อง กำลังลองชุดแต่งงานอยู่หรือ
I'm tired these days. I'll try it on another day.
สองวันนี้เหนื่อยแล้ว วันหลังค่อยลองใหม่
It doesn't matter if you don't.
ไม่ลองก็ไม่เป็นไร
What's this?
นี่คือ
The Cui family runs an illegal private mine,
ตระกูลชุยลักลอบเปิดเหมืองแร่
causing a strange disease in the Beifu Army.
ทำให้เกิดโรคประหลาดในทัพเป๋ยฝู่
Young Lord Xiao has submitted a memorial.
เซียวซื่อจื่อถวายฎีกาแล้ว
County Sheriff Yang Zhang is the witness.
นายอำเภอหยางจางเป็นพยานบุคคล
There's solid evidence.
หลักฐานมัดตัวแน่นหนา
The engagement with one of the Cuis
การหมั้นหมายกับตระกูลชุย
is merely a means to prevent the Princess's political marriage.
ก็แค่วิธีขัดขวางการสมรสเชื่อมสัมพันธ์ ของท่านหญิง
A pawn is sometimes like a piece of clothing.
บางครั้งหมากก็เหมือนเสื้อผ้าตัวหนึ่ง
After it's used and worn,
ใช้เสร็จแล้ว ใส่แล้ว
it should be thrown away.
ถึงเวลาทิ้งก็ต้องทิ้ง
The Cui family will fall in a few days.
ตระกูลชุยจะล่มสลายในอีกไม่กี่วันนี้
But the Cui family is the top noble family in Ye.
แต่ตระกูลชุย เป็นตระกูลใหญ่อันดับหนึ่งของต้าเย่นะ
That was in the past.
นั่นมันอดีต
I will never allow another woman from the Cuis
ข้าไม่มีทางยอมให้สตรีตระกูลชุย
to become the future Empress of Ye.
มาเป็นฮองเฮาในอนาคตของต้าเย่อีกเป็นอันขาด
Fine.
ได้
I will go seize and seal the Cui Mansion myself.
ข้าจะไปปิดจวนตระกูลชุยด้วยตัวเอง
The Empress Dowager won't allow you to mobilize the Imperial Guards.
ไทเฮาไม่มีทางอนุญาต ให้เจ้าเคลื่อนทหารรักษาพระองค์หรอก
Your Highness, you think this alone
แค่สิ่งนี้
can make me mobilize the troops of Prince Jing'an's Household
ท่านอ๋องก็อยากจะให้ข้าสั่งการกองกำลัง
in the name of the Heir's Consort?
ของจวนจิ้งอันอ๋องในนามชายาซื่อจื่อหรือ
Yes.
ใช่
Someone at the imperial court is already
มีคนในราชสำนัก
using the Beifu curse
ยื่นฎีกาถอดถอนอู๋อี๋
to impeach Wuyi.
โดยอ้างเรื่องคำสาปเป๋ยฝู่แล้ว
Not to mention that Wuyi has entered Lingfeng Fort.
อีกอย่างอู๋อีได้เข้าไปในป้อมหลิงเฟิงแล้ว
This is a life-or-death situation.
ศึกครั้งนี้มีแต่สู้กันตายไปข้างหนึ่ง
I can't command the Imperial Guards as they're
ภายใต้การควบคุมของไทเฮา
under the Empress Dowager's control.
ทหารรักษาพระองค์ข้าควบคุมไม่ได้
But tonight, I must seize the Cui Mansion.
แต่คืนนี้ข้าจะต้องยึดจวนตระกูลชุยมาให้ได้
But if you can't find evidence of the Cui family's illegal private mines,
แต่ถ้าหาหลักฐานเหมืองแร่เถื่อน ของจวนตระกูลชุยไม่เจอ
you're dragging Prince Jing'an's Household down with you.
ท่านก็เท่ากับลากจวนจิ้งอันอ๋อง ไปตายด้วยนะ
We can only take a gamble.
คงต้องเสี่ยงสักตั้ง
Xiao Wuyi is also gambling on it.
เซียวอู๋อีเองก็กำลังเสี่ยงอยู่เช่นกัน
I can lend you the men.
กำลัง ข้าให้ท่านยืมได้
Brother Xiao.
พี่ใหญ่ตระกูลเซียว
I dare not be addressed so.
ข้ามิกล้า
I believe
ข้าเชื่อว่า
Wuyi never misjudges anyone.
อู๋อีไม่มีทางมองคนผิด
Since he acknowledges you, Your Highness, as Master,
เขายอมรับท่านอ๋องเป็นนายท่าน
I believe you're of one mind with Wuyi
ข้าก็เชื่อว่าท่านอ๋องกับอู๋อีและสกุลเซียว
and the Xiao family.
ใจเป็นหนึ่งเดียวกัน
You can borrow
กองกำลังเหล่านี้
our troops.
ก็ให้ท่านยืม
If I ever fail you,
หากทรยศ
I, Li Yizhi,
ข้า
will die without a terrible death.
ขอตายอย่างไร้ที่ฝัง
Today,
วันนี้
with the token of the Heir's Consort, I'm ordering you
ข้าในนามชายาซื่อจื่อขอออกคำสั่งพวกเจ้า
to follow Prince Qi
ให้ติดตามท่านอ๋อง
and secretly seal the Cui Mansion in Jiankang.
ไปปิดล้อมตรวจค้นจวนตระกูลชุย แห่งเจี้ยนคังอย่างลับ ๆ
You're all at the command of His Highness, Prince Qi.
การปฏิบัติการทั้งหมดให้ฟังคำสั่งของฉีอ๋อง
-Understood!
- รับทราบ - ร้บทราบ
Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋อง
I'm giving this token to you.
ป้ายคำสั่งมอบให้ท่าน
From this moment on,
นับจากตอนนี้ไป
these troops are at your command.
กองกำลังเหล่านี้จะขึ้นตรงต่อคำสั่งของท่าน
-We'll follow your orders, Your Highness!
- น้อมรับคำสั่งท่านอ๋อง
Three.
สาม
Master,
เรียนนายท่าน
as you expected,
เป็นไปตามที่ท่านคาดการณ์
Prince Qi has obtained the troops of Prince Jing'an's Household
ท่านฉีอ๋องได้กองกำลัง ของจวนจิ้งอันอ๋องมาแล้ว
and is heading to the Cui Mansion.
กำลังมุ่งหน้าไปยังตระกูลชุย
It seems that
ดูท่า
Jiankang will be in chaos again tonight.
คืนนี้เจี้ยนคังจะไม่สงบสุขอีกแล้ว
Master,
นายท่าน
is it a bit too late to take out
สินสอดเอาออกมาตอนนี้
the betrothal gifts now?
จะช้าไปหน่อยหรือเปล่าขอรับ
After tonight,
หลังผ่านคืนนี้ไป
the Cui family and Prince Qi will surely be bitter enemies.
ตระกูลชุยกับฉีอ๋อง จะต้องอยู่ร่วมโลกกันไม่ได้แน่
These are betrothal gifts prepared for Prince Qi.
นี่เป็นสินสอดที่เตรียมไว้ให้ฉีอ๋อง
Who said they were for the Cui family?
ใครบอกว่าให้ตระกูลชุยกัน
It has been 22 years.
ยี่สิบสองปีแล้ว
Cui Jun has hidden so deeply.
ชุยจวิ้นซ่อนตัวได้ลึกลับขนาดนี้
Don't worry, they are all following.
วางใจเถอะ พวกเขาตามมาอยู่
Brother,
ท่านพี่
we should have a death squad of our own.
เราควรมีหน่วยกล้าตายเป็นของตัวเองนะ
You must have a death squad of your own,
ท่านต้องมีหน่วยกล้าตายเป็นของตัวเอง
one that belongs to no one else
ที่ไม่ขึ้นตรงต่อผู้ใด
but only to you.
ขึ้นตรงต่อท่านแต่เพียงผู้เดียวนะ
Lejun,
เล่อจวิน
are you scared?
เจ้ากลัวไหม
Brother,
ท่านพี่
other noble families will also have
สิ่งที่จวนจิ้งอันอ๋องมี
what Prince Jing'an's Household owns.
ตระกูลขุนนางอื่น ๆ ก็มีเช่นกัน
Today's Imperial Guards are weak.
ตอนนี้กองกำลังทหารรักษาพระองค์อ่อนแอมาก
Otherwise, Prince Changsha wouldn't
ไม่งั้นฉางซาอ๋องตอนนั้น
have broken through the palace gates so easily back then.
คงบุกทลายประตูวังไม่ได้ง่าย ๆ
We...
พวกเรา...
Really?
จริงหรือ
Since we are joining the game,
ในเมื่อก้าวเข้ามาในกระดานหมากแล้ว
we can no longer be pawns.
จะเป็นแค่หมากอีกต่อไปไม่ได้
Don't worry, Lejun.
วางใจเถอะเล่อจวิน
I am learning to be a player.
ข้ากำลังเรียนรู้วิธีที่จะเป็นผู้เดินหมาก
I will never be
ชีวิตนี้
manipulated by anyone again for the rest of my life.
จะไม่ยอมให้ใครมาบงการอีกต่อไป
But tonight,
เพียงแต่คืนนี้
it's more appropriate to leave it to the men
มอบให้คนของจวนจิ้งอันอ๋องลงมือ
of Prince Jing'an's Household.
จะเหมาะสมกว่า
Today, we're luring the Cui family into the trap
วันนี้ที่ล่อตระกูลชุยเข้ามาในกับดัก
and using Xiao Wuyi and the Beifu Army as bait.
ใช้เซียวอู๋อีและกองทัพเป๋ยฝู่เป็นเหยื่อล่อ
I only want to see if the Cui family would
ก็แค่อยากเห็นตระกูลชุย จะขุดหลุมฝังตัวเองหรือไม่
dig their own grave.
ก็เท่านั้น
Prince Qi?
ฉีอ๋อง
How come it's you?
ทำไมถึงเป็นท่านล่ะ
It's nothing.
ไม่มีอะไร
I just thought about how unpleasant my previous visits
ก็แค่คิดถึงครั้งก่อน ๆ ที่มาจวนตระกูลชุย
to the Cui Mansion were.
ในใจรู้สึกไม่ค่อยสบอารมณ์
Now I want to vent my anger,
ตอนนี้อยากจะระบายความอัดอั้นนี้ออกมา
so I came here.
ข้าก็เลยมาน่ะ
The Cui family and your family
ตระกูลชุยและฉีอ๋องสองตระกูล
are having a marriage alliance.
จะเกี่ยวดองกัน
Now you've raided the Cui Mansion at night.
ตอนนี้ท่านบุกค้นจวนตระกูลชุยยามวิกาล
Aren't you afraid the ruined marriage
ไม่กลัวว่างานแต่งจะล่ม
will turn you into a laughingstock?
ถูกคนใต้เหล้าหัวเราะเยาะหรือ
Your Highness!
ท่านฉีอ๋อง
The Cuis incited rumors of the Beifu curse,
ตระกูลชุยปลุกปั่นเรื่องคำสาปทัพเป๋ยฝู่
attempting to sabotage the reform.
คิดจะทำลายการปฏิรูป
Their crimes are unforgivable.
จิตใจชั่วร้ายสมควรตาย
Now, seize everyone in the Cui Mansion.
จับกุมคนจวนตระกูลชุยทั้งหมดทันที
Dead or alive,
ไม่ว่าจะเป็นหรือตาย
no one is allowed to leave the Cui Mansion.
ก็ห้ามก้าวออกจากจวนตระกูลชุย แม้แต่ก้าวเดียว
-Understood!
- รับทราบ
Do you have any evidence?
หลักฐานล่ะ
Evidence?
หลักฐานหรือ
That depends on what we can find
งั้นก็ต้องดูว่าคืนนี้
in the Cui Mansion tonight.
จะค้นเจออะไรในจวนตระกูลชุยแล้ว
I've wanted to do this for many years.
ข้าอยากทำแบบนี้มาหลายปีแล้ว
What a pity.
น่าเสียดาย
You've survived for over a decade more.
ที่ปล่อยให้เจ้ามีชีวิตอยู่มาตั้งสิบกว่าปี
[Lingfeng Fort]
[ป้อมหลิงเฟิง]
"Tomb Raider"?
นักขุดสุสาน
Do you really think
เจ้าคิดว่า
I'm as stupid as my foolish brother
ข้าจะโง่เหมือนน้องชายปัญญานิ่มของข้า
and don't know you actually are
ที่ไม่รู้ว่าเจ้า
Grand Tutor Xie's daughter, Xie Jiayu?
คือเซี่ยเจียอวี๋ บุตรีของราชครูเซี่ยอย่างนั้นหรือ
I heard that you are Prince Qi's beloved
ได้ยินว่าเจ้าเป็นคนรักของท่านฉีอ๋อง
and later married the Heir of Prince Jing'an, Xiao Wuyi.
ต่อมาก็แต่งงานกับซื่อจื่อเซียวอู๋อี
Now,
และตอนนี้
you are in a secret relationship
ก็มาพัวพันกับองครักษ์
with this guard named Da.
ที่ชื่ออาต้าคนนี้อีก
You're really something.
ลูกไม้เจ้าไม่เบาเลยนะ
Let her go!
ปล่อยนางนะ
Chug down this drug,
เจ้าดื่มยานี่ลงไปดี ๆ
and I'll let her go.
ข้าก็จะปล่อยนางไป
What are you going to do?
เจ้าจะทำอะไร
Are you okay?
ท่านเป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
This is the strongest aphrodisiac.
นี่คือยาปลุกกำหนัดที่ฤทธิ์แรงที่สุด
As strong and vigorous as he is,
ข้าเห็นเขาร่างกายแข็งแรงกำยำ กระปรี้กระเปร่า
it's perfect for him, I think.
เหมาะกับของสิ่งนี้ที่สุดแล้ว
How do you feel?
ท่านรู้สึกอย่างไรบ้าง
Tell me.
พูดมา
Who on earth are you?
เจ้าเป็นใครกันแน่
Where are your two accomplices?
ผู้ช่วยของเจ้าสองคนนั่นตอนนี้อยู่ที่ไหน
What are you up to in Lingfeng Fort?
พวกเจ้ามาที่ป้อมหลิงเฟิง มีจุดประสงค์อะไรกันแน่
Eldest Young Lady Cui,
คุณหนูใหญ่ชุย
how long are you going to keep up this show?
ละครฉากนี้เจ้าจะเล่นไปอีกนานแค่ไหน
If you truly wanted to hurt us,
หากเจ้าคิดจะทำร้ายพวกข้าจริง ๆ
why didn't you just hand us over to Cui Shao'an?
ไยไม่ส่งตัวพวกข้าให้ชุยเส้าอันเล่า
This aphrodisiac is just a blood-invigorating medicine.
ยาปลุกกำหนัดนี่ก็แค่ยาบำรุงเลือด
Added with Chuanxiong,
ผสมกับโกฐหัวบัว
it can cause a temporary surge of qi and blood,
แม้จะทำให้เลือดลมพลุ่งพล่านชั่วขณะ
but it also has a detoxifying effect.
แต่ก็มีฤทธิ์ถอนพิษ
You are not a bad person.
เจ้าไม่ใช่คนไม่ดี
Young Lord Xiao, you didn't show your true identity.
เซียวซื่อจื่อไม่ยอมเผยโฉมหน้าที่แท้จริงเลย
So how could you expect me to be honest?
แล้วจะให้ลิ่งอี๋เปิดใจได้อย่างไรกัน
You know who I am?
เจ้ารู้ว่าข้าเป็นใคร
What exactly do you want?
เจ้าคิดจะทำอะไรกันแน่
I want you to destroy the Cui family.
ข้าอยากให้พวกท่านทำลายตระกูลชุยซะ
But you are about to marry into the Crown Prince's family.
แต่เจ้ากำลังจะแต่งเข้าตำหนักบูรพาแล้วนะ
I assume you have also seen
คิดว่าพวกท่านก็คงจะเห็น
the girls in the mines.
พวกสตรีในเหมืองแล้วสินะ
The crimes committed by my father
บาปที่ท่านพ่อข้าก่อขึ้น
will come to light sooner or later.
สักวันหนึ่งจะต้องถูกเปิดโปงให้ใต้หล้ารู้
By then,
ถึงตอนนั้น
the Cui family, the top noble family in the world,
ตระกูลชุยตระกูลอันดับหนึ่งในใต้หล้า
will be utterly doomed.
จะต้องพบกับหายนะอย่างแน่นอน
So I'd like to ask you two
ดังนั้นข้าจึงอยากขอให้ท่านทั้งสอง
to help our Cui family return to the right path.
ช่วยตระกูลชุยกลับสู่หนทางที่ถูกต้อง
Why should we trust you?
พวกข้าจะเชื่อเจ้าได้อย่างไร
It's my mother's jade pendant.
ป้ายหยกของท่านแม่ข้านี่
You have met my mother?
เจ้าเคยพบท่านแม่ข้าหรือ
Is she trapped here by Cui Shao'an?
นางถูกชุยเส้าอันขังไว้ที่นี่ใช่ไหม
I hid Her Highness.
ข้าเป็นคนซ่อนท่านหญิงไว้เอง
I know you are Xie Jiayu
เหตุที่ข้ารู้ว่าเจ้าคือเซี่ยเจียอวี๋
because I saved Her Highness.
ก็เพราะว่าข้าได้ช่วยท่านหญิงไว้
Her Highness discovered the mines and could have escaped,
ท่านหญิงค้นพบถ้ำเหมือง เดิมทีสามารถหนีไปได้
but to save the girls in the mines,
แต่เพื่อช่วยพวกสตรีในถ้ำเหมือง
she ended up in danger
เลยตกอยู่ในอันตราย
and was hunted down by my father.
ถูกท่านพ่อข้าตามไล่ล่า
Her Highness asked me to write to you.
ท่านหญิงให้ข้าเขียนสารถึงเจ้า
She said that as long as the letter was delivered to Prince Jing'an's Mansion,
นางบอกว่าขอเพียงส่งสารนี้ถึงจวนจิ้งอันอ๋อง
the Heir of Prince Jing'an, Xiao Wuyi,
ซื่อจื่อเซียวอู๋อี
would figure out that she was in danger in the mine.
ก็จะรู้ว่านางตกอยู่ในอันตรายที่ถ้ำเหมือง
I just didn't expect you to come, too.
เพียงแต่คิดไม่ถึงว่าเจ้าก็มาด้วย
Since you are already here...
ในเมื่อมากันแล้ว
So you want to make a move tonight?
เจ้าก็เลยคิดจะลงมือคืนนี้
I have spread the news that
ข้าปล่อยข่าวออกไปแล้ว
the Heir of Prince Jing'an and Lady Jiayu have escaped from Lingfeng Fort.
ว่าซื่อจื่อกับคุณหนูหนีออกจากป้อมหลิงเฟิง
Now, my brother has recovered from the needle poison.
ตอนนี้น้องชายข้าฤทธิ์เข็มสลายแล้ว
He will definitely go out of the city to catch you.
เขาจะต้องออกจากเมืองไปตามจับแน่นอน
Whoever catches Xiao Wuyi and Xie Jiayu
ผู้ที่จับตัวเซียวอู๋อีกับเซี่ยเจียอวี๋ได้
will be rewarded with 100 taels of gold!
รับรางวัลเงินหนึ่งร้อยตำลึง
That will be the perfect chance to bring down my father.
ถึงตอนนั้นก็จะเป็นโอกาสดีที่สุด ที่จะโค่นล้มท่านพ่อข้า